Guide to the Britton Harris papers, 1952-1988
Harris, Britton papers, 1952-1988
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Britton Harris papers, 1952-1988
4255
Britton Harris, 1914-
.6 cubic ft.
Articles and other publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Articles and other publications by Britton Harris on land use development, transportation, use of computers, and various other topics in planning and regional science.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
A city planner, Britton Harris is Emeritus Professor of Planning at the University of Pennsylvania.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Articles and other publications by Britton Harris on land use development, transportation, use of computers, and various other topics in planning and regional science. Part of Regional Science Archives.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Harris, Britton, 1914-
Subjects:
City planning.; Regional science.
Form and Genre Terms:
Resumes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- "The Role of Government in Industrial Development in the Caribbean", Oct. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Preliminary version of talk delivered at the West Indian Conference of the Caribbean Commission in Nov. 1952
- "The Economics of the Base Study" by Sue S. Moyerman and Britton Harris., Oct. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Taken from a study being conducted by the Institute for Urban Studies, University of Pennsylvania, for the Philadelphia City Plan Commission.
- "Notes on Tax Exemption and Development," reprinted from National Tax Journal, VII, No. 4, Dec. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Projecting Industrial Growth of Metropolitan Regions", Feb. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Revised version of a paper delivered at the Dec. 1955 meetings of the Association of Regional Scientists, New York.
- "Needed Studies for the Analysis of Water Requirements and Utilization", Dec. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  A report to the Delaware River Basin Advisory Committee from the Institute for Urban Studies, University of Pennsylvania.
- Memorandum: "Interrelationship of Measurements of Geographic Distribution," Institute for Urban Studies, University of Pennsylvania., May 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Paper: "Research and Education in Physical Planning for Underdeveloped Areas", May 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Memorandum: "Philadelphia Industrial Land and Facilities Project", May 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Reprint: "Comment on Pfout's Test of the Base Theory," Journal of the American Institute of Planners, Vol. 24, No. 4, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Problems Related to Real Estate Taxes", May 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Memorandum to members of Ford Foundation Team
- "Note on the Relation of City Planning to Broad Social Goals", May 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Urbanization Policy in India," Papers and Proceedings of the Regional Science Association, Volume 5, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Some Implications of India in Urban Problems in the Third Five Year Plan", Mar. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Plan or Projection: An Examination of the Use of Models in Planning," reprinted from The Journal of American Institute of Planners, Vol. XXVI, No. 4, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Some Problems in the Theory of Intra-Urban Location," reprinted from Operations Research, Vol. 9, No. 5, Sept.-Oct. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Experiments in Projection of Transportation and Land Use," reprinted from Traffic Quarterly, Apr. 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Economic Aspects of Metropolitan Planning," reprinted from Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, Vol. 106, No. 3, June 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "An Accounts Framework for Intermetropolitan Models", Nov. 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Paper prepared for the Conference on Regional Accounts Held by the Committeee on Regional Accounts at Miami, Florida
- Penn Jersey Transportation Study: "Linear Programming and the Projection of Land Uses", Nov. 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Have We Learned Anything from Transportation Studies?", May 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "A Note on the Probability of Interaction at a Distance," Journal of Regional Science, Vol. 5, No. 2, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Preliminary Research Proposal for Project 8-4: "Criteria for Evaluating Alternative Transportation Plans", Aug. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Submitted to Highway Research Board; National Academy of Science; National Research Council, with Russell L. Ackoff
- Penn Jersey Transportation Study: "Decision-Oriented Models of Metropolitan Growth", Mar. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Proceedings of the 39th Annual Conference of the American Industrial Development Council" (partial copy), Apr. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Preliminary Research Proposal for Project 8-4: Criteria for Evaluation Alternative Transportation Plans", Aug. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Submitted to Highway Research Board, National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council
- "A Model of Locational Equilibrium for Retail Trade", Oct. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "A Note on the Probability of Interaction at a Distance," reprinted from Journal of Regional Science, Vol. 5, No. 2, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Models Development in Relation to Administration and Technological Innovation" in Management Information Technology: Recent Advances and Implications for Public Administration, a Symposium based on papers presented at the 1964 National Conference on Public Administration, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Guest Editor, Special Issue Journal of the American Institute of Planners, Vol. XXXI, No. 2, "Urban Development Models: New Tools for Planning", May 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Organizing the Use of Models in Metropolitan Planning", Mar. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Paper presented at a Seminar on Metropolitan Land Use Models sponsored by the California State Office of Planning with support from the Urban Renewal Administration
- "Notes on an Approach to Metropolitan Housing Market Analysis," Institute for Urban Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Apr. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter to Professor Gerald Hodge, Division of Town and Regional Planning, University of Toronto, Mar. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Memorandum to Grigsby, Tomazinis, Ukeles, Mar. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Memorandum to Research Council, Graduate School of Fine Arts Faculty, Department of City and Regional Planning: "Notes on a Postion on the Quantitative Method", Mar. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Memorandum to Research Council, Graduate School of Fine Arts Faculty, Department of City and Regional Planning: "Notes on a Position on the Quantitative Method", Mar. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Note on Residential Location in a Subnucleated Region," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Mar. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Note on Residential Mixture in the Herbert-Stevens Model," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Apr. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Urban Transportation Planning: Philosophy of Approach", May 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Paper presented at the national Transportation Symposium and Railroad Conference, sponsored by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, San Francisco, Califorrnia, published ASME, United Engineering Center, New York, New York
- "Notes on Accessibility," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, June 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Basic Assumptions for a Simulation of the Urban Residential Housing and Land Market," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, July 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Book review of Measuring Benefits of Government Investments, edited by Robert Dorman, Journal of the American Institute of Planners, July 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Note on Aspects of Equilibrium in Urban Growth Models," preliminary draft, Aug. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The Uses of Theory in the Simulation of Urban Phenomena," Journal of the American Institute of Planners, XXXII, No. 5, Sept. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Memorandum to Faculty, Department of City Planning and Regional Planning: "Computer Gaming", Oct. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Memorandum to Faculty, Graduate School of Fine Arts: "Design Research", Oct. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Inventing the Future Metropolis," published in Shaping an Urban Future: Essays in Memory of Catherine Bauer Wurster (photocopy), Oct. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The City of the Future: The Problem of Optimal Design", Nov. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Comment by Ira S. Lowry read at the Annual Meeting of the Regional Science Association, West Clayton, Missouri
- "The City of the Future: The Problem of Optimal Design," Papers and Proceedings of the Regional Science Association, XIX, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Metropolitan Development and Transportation Planning by Robert B. Mitchell and Britton Harris, Center for Planning & Development Research: Institute of Urban & Regional Development, University of California, Berkeley, Dec. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "How to Succeed with Computers without Really Trying," Journal of the American Institute of Planners, XXXIII, No. 1, Jan. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Memorandum to files: "Reprogramming AID: University of Michigan Program for Grouping Obserations", Feb. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Future Technology: Servant or Master?", Apr. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Remarks made at Second International Conference on Urban Transportation, panel on "Future Modes of Transportation," sponsored by the Pittsburgh Council for Urban Transportation, Pittsburgh
- Paper: "Urban Development Models", c. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Computer Needs for Urban Research", June 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Note on Two Transportation Facility Locational Problems", July 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Memorandum to files: "Household Transition Probability Model", July 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Book review of Urban Atlas: 20 American Cities: A Communication Study Notating Selected Urban Data at a Scale of 1:48,000 by Joseph R. Passoneau and Richard Saul Wurman, July 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Transportation and Urban Goals", Apr. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Paper presented at Symposium of "Science, Engineering, and the City," sponsored by the National Academy of Engineering, Washington, D.C.
- "The University and the Problems of Urbanism", Nov. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Paper presented at Urban Affairs conference of the Council on Economic Growth, Technology, and Public Policy of the Committee on Institutional Cooperation, Chicago, Ill.
- Memorandum to Computer Center, Faculty Advisory Committee on Computing Facilites: "Conversion to 360 Operation", Sept. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Organized Activities by Users of the University of Pennsylvania Compuer Facilities", Oct. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Computers and Urban Planning," reprinted from Socio-Economic Planning Sciences, Vol. 1, Pergamon Press, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "The New Technology and Urban Planning," reprinted from Urban Research and Policy Planning, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "The Limits of Science and Humanism in Planning," Journal of the American Institute of Planners, Sept. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "A Model of Household Locational Preferences", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Report of Dartmouth Conference on Urban Development Models", Jan. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Paper presented at 49th Annual Meetings of the Highway Research Board, Washington, D.C.
- "Report on OECD Meeting, London, Dec. 4-5, 1967 ," by U.S. Representatives Britton Harris and Melvin M. Webber, Jan. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Computers and Urban Decision-making", May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Paper prepared from Task Force on Economic Growth and Opportunity
- "A Technology of Social Progress," The American Behavioral Scientist, July-Aug. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Preliminary Report on Household Projection Model," Planning Sciences Group, Institute for Environmental Studies, Graduate School of Fine Arts, University of Pennsylvania, Sept. 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "New Tools for Research and Analysis in Urban Planning", Oct. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Paper presented at 1968 National Conference of the American Institute of Planners, Pittsburgh, Pa.
- "Quantitative Models of Urban Development: Their Role in Metropolitan Policy Making," Issues in Urban Economics, Harvey S. Perloff and Lowdon Wingo, Jr., eds., Resources for the Future, Ind. The Johns Hopkins Press, Baltimore, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Final Report on Household Projection Model", May 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Report to the Bureau of Public Roads
- "People, Problems and Plans: The Purpose and Nature of Design," Transactions of the Bartlett Society, Vol. 7. School of Environmental Studies, University College, London, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "The Impact of the BARTD System on Metropolitan Land Uses", Feb. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "The Planning Process as a Mathematical Program", Sept. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Paper presented at First Conference of Italian Section of the Regional Science Association, Rome
- "Program Write-ups for Household Projection Model: General Information for Household Transition Projection Model", Sept. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Supplementary Report on Household Projection Model," with William C. Wheaton, Oct. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Experimental Investigation of a Combinatorial Problem," with Andre Farhi and Jean Dufour, Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Dec. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Planning Models - Pure but not Simple," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Dec. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Generating Projects for Urban Research," Environment and Planning, Vol. 2, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Review of Urban Planning in the Developing Countries, reprinted from Economical Development and Cultural Change, Vol. 19, No. 2, Jan. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Final Report, "The Widening Role of Urban Transportation Planning," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Feb. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Planning as a Branch and Bound Process", Aug. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Paper presented at Tenth European Regional Science Association Conference, London
- "Branch-and-Bound in Space Allocation," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Apr. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "A Critique of Census Tape Processing Centers," with Leonora McCaffrey, Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Oct. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Two New Algorithms for the Transportation Problem," Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Dec. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Aspects of a Problem in Clustering," with Andre Farhi and Jean Dufour, Institute for Environmental Studies, University of Pennsylvania, Jan. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "The Transportation Needs of Urban Systems", Mar. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Paper presented at 1972 Inter-Societal Conference on Transportation, Washington
- "Note on the Application of Locational Constraints in Repetitive Calculations", June 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Indirect Impacts of Urban Decisions", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Draft of paper prepared from presentation at a conference of the Joint Institute on Comparative Urban and Grants Economics, in Augsburg, Aug. 20-25, 1972
- "Space Allocation Methods in the Design Process", Aug. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Paper presented at London meetings of the Regional Science Association
- "Computer Simulations of the Metropolis", Dec. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Paper presented at Fall Joint Computer Conference, Los Angeles
- "Externalities and Urban Decision-Making," Spatial, Regional and Population Economics: Essays in Honor of Edgar M. Hoover, Mark Perlman, Charles J. Leven, and Benjamin Chinitz, eds., Gordon and Breach, New York, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "The Need for Explicit Procedures of Transportation Plan-Making", Jan. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Paper presented at meetings of the Highway Research Board, Washington, D.C.
- "Large-Scale Models of Urban Location and Transportation", Feb. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Paper presented at Environmental Management Conference, San Diego
- "Comprehensiveness in Transportation Education", Sept. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Paper presented at Conference on Multidisciplinary Education in Transportation, co-sponsored by the Highway Research Board Task Force on Multidisciplinary Education in Transportation Planning and the University of Pennsylvania Transportation Studies Center, Philadelphia. Published in Special Report 150, Transportation Research Board, National Research Council, Washington, D.C.
- "Regional and Urban Planning as an Optimizing Process", Dec. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Paper presented at Third World Congress of Engineers and Architects in Israel, Dialogue in Development - Natural and Human Resources, June 1974
- "Heuristics and Design," reprinted from Papers of the Regional Science Association, Vol. 31, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Model-Building and Rationality", July 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Opening Address, International Conference on Urban Development Models, Churchill College, Cambridge, England
- "Values in the Making of the Environment", Feb. 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Lecture given at the University of Pennsylvania
- "A Fundamental Paradigm for Planning," Department of City and Regional Planning, Papers in Planning Theory, University of Pennsylvania, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Bridging the Gap Between Theory and Practice in Urban Planning", Oct. 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Paper presented at Conference on the Use of Models by Planning Agencies, Fels Center Government, School of Public and Urban Policy, University of Pennsylvania
- "Speeding up Iterative Algorithms - The Generalized Weber Problem," Journal of Regional Science, Vol. 16, No. 3, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "The Comprehensive Planning of Location", Sept. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Paper presented at "Planning: Challenge & Response," a conference sponsored by The Center for Urban Policy Research, Rutgers University, New Brunswick
- "A Note on Planning Theory," Environment and Planning A, Vol. 10, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Equilibrium values and dynamics of attractiveness terms in production-constrained spatial-interaction models," Environment and Planning A, Vol. 10, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "A New Algorithm for Tree Modification in the Primal Transportation Problem," Transportation Science, Vol. 12, No. 4, Nov. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Aggregation in Models of Transportation and Land Use", June 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Paper presented at Conference on Urban Transportation, Planning, and the Dynamics of Land Use, Transportation Center, Northwestern University
- "Algorithm 5: Gradient search on an N-dimensional surface," Environment and Planning A, volume 10, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Planning Requirements for a New Order", May 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Paper presented at Conference on Planning Theory, "The Structural Crises of the 1970s and Beyond: The Need for a New Planning Theory," Division of Environmental and Urban Systems, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
- "Regional Science and Urban Planning", Nov. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Paper presented at Twenty-Fifth North American Meetings of the Regional Science Association, Chicago
- "Social Requirements for a New Order", Apr. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Paper presented at Conference on Planning Theory and Practice: Economic Context, Emerging Coalitions, and Progressive Planning Roles, Cornell University
- "Current Problems in Regional Science Methodology", Aug. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Paper presented at European Meetings of the Regional Science Association, London (preliminary)
- "Types of Models in Planning and Policy Formation", Oct. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Paper presented at "The Role of Policy Analysis in the Education of Planners," a symposium held by the Department of Urban Studies, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
- "A rapid dual method for the Hitchcock problem," Environment and Planning A, volume 11, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Algorithms for the Transportation Problem", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Algorithm 10: Inverting a symmetrical matrix in plane," Environment and Planning A, volume 12, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Regional Theory in a Modeling Environment", Mar. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Paper presented at Regional Development Conference on "Theoretical and Practical Aspects of Regional Development Modeling," International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, Schloss Laxenburg, Austria
- "Notes on the Urban-Rural Interface in India" (preliminary draft), Jan. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Health and Ecology in Urban Habitats", May 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Paper prepared for "Applications of Human Ecology in Development," a symposium sponsored by the Society of Human Ecology and the PAHO Center for Human Ecology and Health, Toluca, Mexico
- "Theory and the Practice of Planning and Design," Umea, Sweden, June 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Spatial Analysis: Some Working Principles", June 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Paper presented at Conference, Structural Economic Analysis and Planning in Time and Space, University of Umea, Sweden
- "Policy-Making, Programming Experience," Research in Public Policy Analysis and Management, Volume 14, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Economies of scale and the existence of supply-side equilibria in a production-constrained spatial-interaction model," with J-M Choukroun, and A.G. Wilson, Environment and Planning A, volume 14 (also reprint), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Scientific Aspects of Innovation: Potentials and Limits", Feb. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Edited transcript of a lecture at the School of Planning, College of Design, Art, Architecture, and Planning, University of Cincinnati
- "Elements in a Planning Education", Oct. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Paper prepared for a conference of the Associated Collegiate Schools of Planning, San Francisco
- "Post-Industrial Urban Policy: Reviewing the Background", July 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Paper prepared for a conference on Transportation and Land-Use Modeling, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada
- "Interdisciplinary Disciplines," Geographical Analysis, vol. 15, no. 1, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Models and Rational Action", Oct. 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Paper prepared for the meetings of the Association of Collegiate Schools of Planning, New York (preliminary)
- "Economical Development, Decentralization and Agglomeration," in Spatial, Environmental, and Resource Policy in the Developing Countries, Chatterji, Nijkamp, Lakshmanan, and Pathak, eds. Aldershop, Hampshire, U.K: Gower, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Some notes on parallel computing: with special reference to transportation and land-use modeling," Environment and Planning A, volume 17, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Cities and Regions in the Electronic Age", Aug. 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Paper prepared for a workshop in Melbourne, Australia
- "Synthetic geography: the nature of our understanding of cities," First "Environment and Planning" lecture, Environment and Planning A, volume 17, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Does the Third World Need Computers?", Nov. 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Paper presented at the joint meetings of ORSA/TIMS, Atlanta
- "Urban Simulation Models in Regional Science," Journal of Regional Science, Vol. 25, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Sources and Styles of Originality in Regional Science", Nov. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Paper prepared for the 33rd Annual Meetings of the North American Section of the Regional Science Association, Columbus, Ohio
- "A Continuous Dual Method for the Hitchcock Problem," from "Short Notes and Research Communications," Transportation Research-B, Vol. 20B, No. 1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Hierarchies and Decomposition in Planning", Aug. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Paper prepared for the 33rd Annual Meetings of the Regional Science Association, Columbus, Ohio